http://youtu.be/vNHHbwzKdJo
http://youtu.be/vNHHbwzKdJo Tung Dinh - VGU
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, Jon, what are we going to learn today?
Hey, Jon, Hôm nay ta học gì?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Today, we're going to learn our first try at communicating
Hôm nay, ta sẽ học về giao tiếp
between devices, between two or more devices using the UART, which
giữa các thiết bị, 2 hay nhiều thiết bị dùng UART
stands for Universal Asynchronous Receiver Transmitter.
UART nghĩa là máy thu phát đa năng phổ quát
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So does universal mean
Vậy  phổ quát nghĩa là
that all devices communicate this way?
nó có thể giao tiếp với mọi thiết bị à
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: No, the UART is one of the first,
Không, UART là 1 trong những phương pháp đầu tiên
or one of the original, communication protocols using what's called RS-232.
về giao thức giao tiếp sử dụng RS-232
And we will use it because it is quite simple.
và ta sẽ dùng nó vì tính đơn giản
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So it must be easy to learn then?
Vậy, nó phải đễ học phải không?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes, especially compared to something like TCP/IP,
Vâng, đặc biệt khi so sánh với TCP/IP
the one used for the internet, which is extremely complex.
phương thức dùng trong internet, cực kì phức tạp
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Is it because it has
Bởi vì
to account for all kinds of devices that have to communicate with each other?
nó dùng cho mọi loại thiết bị
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
Vâng
In our case, we'll use a simple protocol where
Trong trường hợp này, ta sẽ dùng phương thức đơn giản
two devices are connected with one serial cable.
mà 2 thiết bị kết nối qua 1 cáp serial
And we'll transmit information from one to the other.
Và ta sẽ truyền tải thông tin từ cái này sang cái kia
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we're going to build something exciting this time?
Nghe thật là thú vị
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
Chắc chắn!
Let's build a chat room.
Rồi, giờ ta làm 1 chat room
I will use one launch pad.
Tôi sẽ dùng 1 mạch
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And I'll use another.
Và tôi sẽ dùng cái này
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And we will be able to ask and answer questions
Và chúng tôi có thể hỏi và trả lời
by communicating between each other--
bằng việc giao tiếp giữa 2 người
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Using a simple interface of the launch pad.
Sử dụng giao diện đơn giản của mạch
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
Vâng
This way, we'll have our own private communication channel.
Cách này, ta sẽ có 1 kênh chat riêng tư
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's do it.
Tiến hành thôi
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes!
Ok!